

# David Semedo

PhD · Assistant Researcher · Multimodal Deep Learning

Lisbon, Portugal

□ (+351) 917620446 | ■ df.semedo@fct.unl.pt | ★ https://davidsemedo.com/ | 🎓 Google Scholar |

thttps://www.linkedin.com/in/david-semedo | thttps://github.com/davidfsemedo

# Summary \_

PhD Assistant Researcher focused on Deep Learning approaches for Multimedia and Natural Language Processing.

His Ph.D. topic focused on computationally bridging vision and language over time, by modeling multimodal data interactions and their evolution, using deep learning architectures and large-scale data collections. Currently investigating open and domain-specific dialog systems, based on deep learning architectures, using data-driven approaches.

Expertise and Interests: deep learning and machine learning for multimedia, natural language processing and data mining.

# **Work Experience**

## Senior Researcher - CMU Portugal iFetch Project

Sept. 2020 - PRESENT

**NOVA SCHOOL OF SCIENCE AND TECHNOLOGY** 

Lisbon, Portugal

- Domain-specific multimodal dialog agents.
- · Neural approaches for multimodal dialog systems.

# Research Assistant - GoLocal Project (CMUP-ERI/TIC/0046/2014)

Jan. 2019 - Aug. 2020

**NOVA SCHOOL OF SCIENCE AND TECHNOLOGY** 

Lisbon, Portugal

- Temporal multimodal deep learning methods for cross-modal embedding learning and retrieval.
- Large-scale data mining and natural language processing for text understanding.

# Research Assistant - COGNITUS H2020 project (Ref. 687605)

Jan. 2016 - Dez. 2018

NOVA SCHOOL OF SCIENCE AND TECHNOLOGY

- Lisbon, Portugal
- · Deep Learning and Machine Learning methods for multimodal (images/video and text) content semantic analysis and retrieval;
- · Natural Language Processing for keyword extraction and understanding, SPAM filtering, and text search;
- Data mining from large-scale social-media collections;
- Collaboration with BBC R&D, Queen Mary University, Vitec, FORTHNet, FORTH, ARRIS-Pace.

#### **Lab Instructor - LxMLS 2016**

July 2016

INSTITUTO SUPERIOR TÉCNICO, UNIVERSIDADE DE LISBOA

Lisbon, Portugal

• Lab Instructor for Lisbon Machine Learning School 2016 (http://lxmls.it.pt/2016/).

#### Research Assistant - Restrict to Plan (QREN) Project (Ref.34091)

Jul. 2014 - Sep. 2015

NOVA SCHOOL OF SCIENCE AND TECHNOLOGY

Lisbon, Portugal

- · Vehicle Scheduling Problems: Stochastic optimization strategies for large combinatorial problems;
- CPU Parallelization techniques for NUMA-based clusters;
- Collaboration with TECMIC.

#### **Linux Distribution Developer and Maintainer**

Jan. 2013 - Jul 2013

CAIXA MÁGICA SOFTWARE

Lisbon, Portugal

- Debian Packages Full Cycle: creation, compilation, testing and deployment;
- Development of a Debian-based educational Linux distribution Openmillenium Project;
- · Responsible for the administration of Caixa Mágica distributions: package updates integration/compilation and deployment.

#### **Junior Research Assistant**

Feb. 2013 - May 2013

NOVA School of Science and Technology

Lisbon, Portugal

• Intrusion tolerant routing protocols for Ad-hoc Wireless Sensor Networks (IEEE 802.15.4). Advised by Prof. Henrique Domingues.

# **Education**

# **NOVA School of Science and Technology**

Jan. 2016 - Jul. 2020

PH.D., COMPUTER SCIENCE

- Thesis: Bridging Vision and Language over Time with Neural Cross-modal Embeddings.
- · Advisor: João Magalhães.

April 12, 2021 David F. Semedo · Curriculum Vitæ

### **NOVA School of Science and Technology**

M.Sc. Computer Science and Engineering

2013 - 2015

• Thesis: A Public Transport Bus Assignment Problem: Parallel Metaheuristics Assessment;

Advisors: Pedro Barahona and Pedro Medeiros.

## **NOVA School of Science and Technology**

B.Sc. Computer Science and Engineering

2010 - 2013

16 out of 20

# **Publications**

- Ferreira, R., M. Leite, D. Semedo, and J. Magalhães, **Open-Domain Conversational Search Assistant with Transformers**, European Conference on Information Retrieval (ECIR), 2021, Lucca, Italy **(CORE A)**
- Semedo, D., Towards Open-domain Vision and Language Understanding with Wikimedia, In Proceedings of the Web Conference, Wiki Workshop, 2021, Ljubljana, Slovenia
- Semedo, David and João Magalhães, Adaptive Temporal Triplet-Loss for Cross-Modal Embedding Learning, Proceedings of the 28th ACM International Conference on Multimedia, 2020, Seattle, WA, USA (CORE A\*)
- Marcelino, G., D. Semedo, A. Mourão, S. Blasi, M. Mrak, and J. Magalhães, A Benchmark of Visual Storytelling in Social Media, Proceedings of the 2019 ACM on International Conference on Multimedia Retrieval (ICMR), 2019, Ottawa, Canada
- Semedo, D. and J. Magalhães, Dynamic-Keyword Extraction from Social Media, European Conference on Information Retrieval (ECIR), 2019, Cologne, Germany (CORE A)
- Semedo, David and Joao Magalhaes, Cross-Modal Subspace Learning with Scheduled Adaptive Margin Constraints, Proceedings of the 27th ACM International Conference on Multimedia, 2019, Nice, France (CORE A\*)
- Semedo, David and Joao Magalhaes, **Diachronic Cross-Modal Embeddings**, Proceedings of the 27th ACM International Conference on Multimedia, 2019, Nice, France (**CORE A\***)
- Awad, George, Asad Butt, Keith Curtis, Yooyoung Lee, Jonathan Fiscus, Afzad Godil, David Joy, Andrew Delgado, Alan Smeaton, Yvette
  Graham, et al., TRECVID 2018: Benchmarking video activity detection, video captioning and matching, video storytelling linking
  and video search, Proceedings of TRECVID 2018, 2018
- Semedo, D. and J. Magalhaes, **Temporal Cross-Media Retrieval with Soft-Smoothing**, Proceedings of the 26th ACM International Conference on Multimedia (ACM MM), 2018, Seoul, Republic of Korea (**CORE A\***)
- Semedo, D., J. Magalhães, and F. Martins, Inferring User Gender from User Generated Visual Content on a Deep Semantic Space, 2018 26th European Signal Processing Conference (EUSIPCO), 2018, Rome, Italy
- Semedo, D. and J. Magalhães, Convolutional Neural Networks for Medical Image classification NovaSearch at ImageCLEFmed 2016
   Subfigure Classification Task, Working Notes of CLEF 2016 Conference and Labs of the Evaluation forum, 2016, Évora, Portugal
- Semedo, D., P. Barahona, and P. Medeiros, Asynchronous Parallel Ant-Colony Optimization Strategies: Application to the Multi-Depot Vehicle Scheduling Problem with Line Exchanges, INForum-Simpósio de Informática (INFORUM). 2015, Covilhã, Portugal

# Awards

2019 Finalist Top-3, AIIA - Altice Innovation Award 2019: Powering Live Event-Plots with Media AI.

2019 **Student Travel Grant**, ACM Multimedia 2019.

Nice, France

# Activities

# Organizer (Local Chair) and Bidder for the premier conference on Multimedia

Lisbon, Portugal

ACM MULTIMEDIA 2022.

Oct. 2022

#### Volunteer at Neural Information Processing Systems (NeurIPS) conference

2020

# **Industry Talk**

TITLE: BRIDGING VISION AND LANGUAGE OVER TIME: TEMPORAL CROSS-MODAL EMBEDDINGS, FARFETCH.

October 2020

# **Webinar Talk**

TITLE: Webinar on "Deep Multimodal and Cross-modal Embeddings", Data Science Portugal (DSPT).

July 2020

## **ECIR 2020 Organization: Local Support**

EUROPEAN CONFERENCE ON INFORMATION RETRIEVAL 2020

April 2020

#### **Seminar Talk**

TITLE: BRIDGING VISION AND LANGUAGE OVER TIME WITH NEURAL CROSS-MODAL EMBEDDINGS, NOVA LINCS SEMINAR.

January 2020

## Poster Presentation at 2nd NOVA Science day

NOVA SCIENCE DAY.

Lisbon 2019

#### Poster Presentation at Encontro Ciência

ANNUAL SCIENCE AND TECHNOLOGY MEETING FOR PORTUGUESE RESEARCHERS.

2016-2019

Lisbon

#### Organizer of TRECVID 2018 Linking Task: Social Media Video Storytelling

Gaithersburg, MD, USA

TRECVID IS THE PREMIER ANNUAL INTERNATIONAL WORKSHOP EVENT FOR EVALUATING CONTENT-BASED RETRIEVAL OF MULTIMEDIA AND DIGITAL VIDEO.

Nov. 2018

· Aimed to advance the area of visual summarization, with collaborative videos, images and texts from professional and social-media users.

#### **EXPO FCT**

SCIENCE FAIR SHOWCASING THE UNIVERSITY RESEARCH FOR HIGH-SCHOOL STUDENTS.

2012, 2016-2019

# **Program Committee and Reviewing Activities**

| 2021 | Reviewer, Association for Computational Linguistics (ACL-IJCNLP)  | Bangkok, Thailand |
|------|---|-------------------|
| 2021 | <b>Program Comittee Member - Reviewer</b> , International Joint Conference on Artificial Intelligence (IJCAI) | Montreal, Canada  |
| 2020 | Program Comittee Member - Reviewer, ACM Multimedia (ACM MM)   | Seattle, USA      |
| 2020 | <b>Journal Reviewer</b> , ACM Transactions on Multimedia Computing, Communications and Applications (Q1)      |                   |
| 2019 | Program Comittee Member - Reviewer, ACM Multimedia (ACM MM)   | Nice, France      |
| 2018 | <b>Reviewer</b> , ACM SIGIR Conference on Research and Development in Information Retrieval (SIGIR)           | Michigan, USA     |
| 2018 | Reviewer, ACM International Conference on Multimedia Retrieval (ICMR)   | Yokohama, Japan   |
| 2018 | Reviewer, International Conference on Theory and Practice of Digital Libraries (TPDL)                         | Porto, Portugal   |
| 2017 | Reviewer, ACM International Conference on Multimedia Retrieval (ICMR)   | Bucharest,Romania |
| 2017 | Reviewer, IEEE International Conference on Multimedia and Expo (ICME)   | Hong Kong         |
| 2016 | Reviewer, ACM International Conference on Multimedia Retrieval (ICMR)   | New York, USA     |

# **Teaching**

2021 Databases, B.Sc. Computer Science course

Information Retrieval (Invited Lecture+Lab), Word Embeddings: Word2vec, skip-grams, Diachronic

Embeddings, BERT, Applications. M.Sc. Computer Science course

2020 **Computational Logic**, B.Sc. Computer Science course

2019 Algorithms and Data Structures, B.Sc. Electrical and Computer Engineering course

2018 Web Search and Data Mining, M.Sc. Computer Science course

2015 Algorithms and Data Structures, B.Sc. Computer Science course

2014 Algorithms and Data Structures, B.Sc. Electrical and Computer Engineering course

# Students Advisoring \_\_\_\_\_

2021 **Ph.D. Rafael Ferreira,** (ongoing) Learning Reinforced Multimodal-Dialog Strategies for Conversational AI Agents, Co-advisor

2021 **M.Sc. Diogo Silva**, (ongoing) Dialog Generation for Recommendation Agents, Co-advisor

2021 M.Sc. Diogo Tavares, (ongoing) Joint Dialog State Tracking and Slot Filling with the Transformer, Co-advisor

M.Sc. Jonas Rodrigues, (ongoing) Metric Learning for Session-based Recommendation in Conversational Systems, Co-advisor

M.Sc. Rafael Ferreira, Tracking Context in Conversational Search: From Utterances to Neural Embeddings, Co-advisor - 20 out of 20

M.Sc. Mariana Ferreira, Knowledge-Driven Answer Generation for Conversational Search, Co-advisor - 19

M.Sc. Ruslan Padnevych, SmartyFlow - Robust Facial Biometrics for Virtual Identification, Co-advisor - 19

# **Computer Literacy**

#### Languages

- Main Programming Languages (Proficient level): Python, C/C++, Java, SQL, Bash;
- Programming Languages: MATLAB, Javascript, OCaml, Prolog, Assembly.

# **Deep Learning, Machine Learning and Data Science**

- **Deep Learning:** PyTorch, Keras, Tensorflow, Hugging Face, Theano;
- Machine Learning and Data Science: Python ML stack: Scipy+Pandas+Scikit-learn+Matplotlib, Statsmodels, XGBoost, Scrapy;
- Vision: OpenCV, Scikit-image, FFmpeg;
- NLP: NLTK Toolkit, Gensim, SpaCy, Tesseract (OCR), Stanford POS Tagger, Stanford NER, WordNet.

# Big Data - Parallel/Distributed/Cloud Computing Libraries and Frameworks

- MPI, OpenMP, HTCondor, Hadoop, Spark, RMI;
- Cloud: Amazon AWS + S3.

# Other Frameworks and Technologies

• LaTeX, RabbitMQ, Docker (Docker Compose), Elasticsearch, Android, GIT.

# **Web Development**

- Frameworks: Django, Flask, Ruby on Rails;
- HTML/XHTML, XML, CSS, JQuery.

## **Computing Infra-structures and Operating Systems**

- Multi-CPU and Multi-GPU deep learning machine setup and management;
- Proficient with Linux (Debian, CentOS) and Windows bash scripting/terminal.